{
  "reference_number": "10142",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If it becomes apparent that the target set is insuffiecient to mitigate serious impacts of climate change then it needs to be revised so\n\n that it is more ambitious. However, if the climate crisis turns out to not be as severe as excpected I don't see any reason to revise the\n target. The target should relust in the introduction of more sustainable, just practises which make for better living conditions accross\n the board."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Yes, but only for a stricter target, the emissions budget should not be able to be increased."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "'Exceptional' meaning that they need to be stricter targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Climate change is one of the biggest challenges facing people in poverty here and in developing countries, the government needs to\n\ninclude these people in the decision making process - making sure that their involvement is accessible. Further afield, we cannot\nhide behind the excuse that Climate Change is a global problem, which cannot be tackled by countries in isolation, and that New\n\nZealand is just one small country. We must demonstrate global leadership and use our international relations to pressure other\ncountries abroad to follow suit. The government needs to acknowledge that our farming culture has to shift. We have to make some\n\ncompromises and not everyone will be pleased with it. The governemnt must ensure that the Zero Carbon Bill is transparent. This\nmeans the bill must include a requirement to produce annual reports about New Zealand’s international climate change contributions\nin order to ensure that the Pacific countries get the support they need and can plan to adapt to their changing environment. This will\n\npromote public engagement and political accountability. New Zealanders will be able to understand the international contributions we\nare making and as a nation, we will be able to stand tall that we are supporting our Pacific neighbours adapt to their climate change\n\nreality."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "No matter what emissions reductions we achieve our society will be subject to consequences of some degree of climate change. We\nwill need to adapt to that."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1. Climate change is one of the biggest challenges facing people in poverty here and in developing countries. We can’t ignore the\nimpact climate change is having on our neighbours in the Pacific and across the developing world. 2. Climate Change is a global\n\nproblem – it cannot be tackled by countries in isolation. New Zealand must demonstrate global leadership and match its bold\ndomestic emissions reduction agenda: by having an equally ambitious climate change strategy abroad. 3. Access to climate finance\nis a matter of climate justice – those who have contributed least to the causes of climate change are typically the most vulnerable to\n\nits impacts and have the least resources to respond. 4. We must take responsibility for our global emissions and the climate impacts\nthat we have contributed to. It’s very important that all New Zealanders have their say on how we make the shift to a zero carbon\n\nfuture here in New Zealand but we must also help the world’s most vulnerable communities across the Pacific adjust to the impacts\non climate change. 5. We must ensure that the Zero Carbon Bill is transparent. This means the bill must include a requirement to\n\nproduce annual reports about New Zealand’s international climate change contributions in order to ensure that the Pacific countries\nget the support they need and can plan to adapt to their changing environment. 6.Transparency in the Bill will promote public\n\nengagement and political accountability. New Zealanders will be able to understand the international contributions we are making and\nas a nation, we will be able to stand tall that we are supporting our Pacific neighbours adapt to their climate change reality. 7. It is time\nfor New Zealand to lead again. We have a history of global leadership: we were the first country to give women the vote and the first\n\nto become nuclear free. It is time to take another giant step towards climate justice globally. 8. New Zealand has demonstrated global\nleadership with our commitment to stopping oil and gas exploration – now let us continue that moral leadership and include\n\ntransparency in what and how we support climate change efforts abroad. 9. Demand that the Zero Carbon Bill supports the most\nvulnerable people in the Pacific!"
    }
  ]
}
